本章，我们讨论一个新概念：抗碰撞
In this module, we're gonna talk about a
new concept called collision resistance,
这在提供信息完整性中扮演着重要角色
which plays an important role in providing
message integrity. Our end goal is to
我们的最终目标是描述一个非常流行的MAC算法，叫做HMAC
describe a very popular MAC algorithm
called HMAC, that's widely used in
HMAC在因特网协议中使用很广。HMAC本身是基于抗碰撞的哈希函数构建的
internet protocols. HMAC itself, is built
from collision resistant hash functions.
在这之前，我们简要回顾一下。上一章节
Before we do that, let's do a quick recap
of where we are. In the last module we
我们讨论了信息完整性，我们说MAC系统是安全的
talked about message integrity where we
said that the MAC system is secure if it's
如果它在选择信息攻击下，是不可被存在性伪造的
existentially unforgeable under a chosen
message attack. This means that even an
这意味着即使一个攻击者有了他选择的任意信息的标签，他也无法构建
attacker who is given the tag on arbitrary
messages of his choice cannot construct a
新的信息标签。然后我们证明了事实上
tag for some new message. And then we
showed that in fact any secure PRF
任何安全PRF都能立即给我们一个安全MAC
immediately gives us a secure MAC. And so
then we turned around and said well can we
我们转而问，能否构建安全PRF，以长信息为输入呢？
build secure PRFs that take large messages
as inputs? And so we looked at four
我们看了四种MAC机制。第一种是基于CBC的
constructions. The first construction was
based on CBC, we call it when we looked at
我们看了它的两种变体，一个叫做加密CBC，一个叫做CMAC
two variants of it, one called encrypted
CBC and one called CMAC. And we said that
我们说过，它们常与AES一起使用。事实上在802.11i标准里
these are commonly used with AES. In fact,
in the 802.11i standard, a CBC-MAC is used
CBC-MAC被用于信息完整性。特别的，配合AES算法
for message integrity. In particular, with
the AES algorithm. We looked at another
我们看另一种模式叫做NMAC，也能把处理短输入的PRF
mode called NMAC, which also converts a
PRF for short inputs into a PRF that's
转变成一个能处理很长信息输入的PRF
capable of taking very large messages as
inputs. And these two were both sequential
两个都是串行的MAC。之后我们看可并行的MAC，叫做PMAC
MAC-s. We then looked at the parallelizable
MAC called PMAC which again was able to
它也可以将处理短输入的PRF，转变成一个能处理很长输入的PRF
convert a PRF for small inputs into a PRF
for very large inputs. But it did so in a
但是它可以并行处理，所以一个多处理器的系统
parallel fashion so a multiprocessor
system would be more efficient with PMAC
使用PMAC的话比使用CBC-MAC更有效。所有这些构建长信息的MAC
than, say, with CBC-MAC. All three of
these built a MAC for large messages by
都是基于长信息的PRF的。然后我们看了Carter-Wegman MAC
constructing a PRF for large messages. And
then we looked at the Carter-Wegman MAC
一个并非基于PRF的MAC。它是一个随机MAC
which is actually not a PRF. It's a
randomized MAC so a single message could
所以单个信息可以有很多不同的有效标签
actually have many, many different valid
tags and therefore a Carter-Wegman MAC is
所以Carter-Wegman MAC不是PRF。如果大家还记得
actually not a PRF. And if you remember,
the Carter-Wegman MAC was built by
首先Carter-Wegman MAC取大量的信息，计算哈希值，得到一个小标签
first of all, taking the bulk message and
hashing it down to a small tag using a
计算是用了快速的一次性MAC，然后用PRF加密
fast one-time MAC and then encrypting that
tag using a PRF. The benefit of the
Carter-Wegman MAC的好处是，我们说过，大量信息的哈希值计算使用了
Carter-Wegman MAC was that, as we said, the
hashing of the bulk message is done using
一个快速的一次性MAC。在本章中，我们将
a fast one time MAC. And then in this
module, we're gonna construct MAC-s from
从抗碰撞这一概念出发，构建MAC
this new concept called collision
resistance. And so the first thing we're
首先我们要构建抗碰撞的哈希函数
gonna do is construct collision resistant
hash functions. So let's first of all
我们首先来定义什么是抗碰撞的哈希函数
start by defining what does it mean for a
hash function to be collision resistant.
考虑一个哈希函数，能将某个信息空间映射到一个标签空间T
So think of a hash function from some
message space to a tag space T, and you
信息空间应当比标签空间大得多
should be thinking of the message space as
much, much bigger than the tag space. So
信息可以是几个G长，但标签只能约160位
the messages could be gigabytes long, but
the tags would only be like 160 bits. Now
函数H的一个碰撞是一对信息（m0,m1）,它们不一样
a collision for the function H is a pair
of messages m0, m1, that happen to be
但是你应用函数H时，你会得到同样的输出
distinct. However, when you apply the
function H to them, you end up with the
所以大家应当记住，有两个输入
same output. So the image you should have
in your mind is essentially there are two
m0和m1，它们同属这个大信息空间。但是
inputs, m0 and m1, and they belong to this
gigantic message space. However, when we
当我们应用这个哈希函数时，它们发生碰撞
apply the hash function to them, they
happen to collide and they both map to the
同被映射到标签空间中的同一个输出。现在我们说这个函数H是抗碰撞的
same output in the tag space. Now we say
that the function is collision resistant
如果很难找到这个函数的碰撞
if it's hard to find collisions for this
function. Now this should seem a little
这有点违背直觉，因为我们知道与输入空间相比
bit counterintuitive because. We know that
the output space is tiny compared to the
输出空间是非常小的。所以根据鸽巢原理，一定有
input space. So, by the pigeonhole
principle, there must be lots and lots and
很多的信息被映射到同样的输出。因为输出空间中
lots of messages that map to the same
output. Just because there isn't enough
没有足够的空间来不碰撞的容纳所有信息
space in the output space to accommodate
all the messages without collisions. And
所以我们知道有很多碰撞，而问题是
so, we know that there are lots of
collisions, and the question is, is there
有没有一个能直接找出这些碰撞的有效算法
an efficient algorithm that finds any such
collisions explicitly. So we say the, the
我们说这个函数H是抗碰撞的，如果对所有的有效算法A
function is collision resistant, if, for
all explicit efficient algorithms A. And
这些算法都不能输出函数H的碰撞
these algorithms are not able to print the
collision for the function H, okay? And as
通常，我们用算法A能够输出一个碰撞的概率
usual, we'll define the advantage as the
probability that the algorithm A is able
来定义这个优势。现在我形式化地描述一下
to output a collision. Now I'm not gonna
formalize a term explicit here. All I'll
我说，仅仅说这种算法是存在的，还远远不够
say is that it's not enough to just say
that an algorithm exists, and algorithm
输出碰撞的算法。以为我们知道有很多碰撞
that simply prints a collision. Cause we
know many collisions exist. What we
我们想要一个直接的算法，可以写下来的算法
actually want is an explicit algorithm
that we can actually write down and run on
并能在计算机上运行，生成碰撞的算法。有一些形式化表述的方法
a computer to generate these collisions.
There are ways to formalize that, but I'm
但我这里不展开说它们。现在一个抗碰撞的哈希函数的例子是SHA-256
not gonna do that here. Now a classic
example of a collision resistant hash
SHA-256输出256位，但可以输入任意长的信息
function is SHA-256 which happens
to output at 256 bits but can take
例如，它可以取几个G的数据
arbitrary large input. For example, it can
take gigabytes and gigabytes of data and
并把输入映射到256位字符串。目前还没有人
it will map it all to 256 bits. And yet
nobody knows how to find collisions for
能为这个函数找出碰撞。这里仅仅是为大家证明
this particular function. So just to show
you that this concept of collision
这个碰撞的概念是非常有用的，我们看一个简单应用
resistance is very useful, let's see a
very quick application for it. In
特别地，给定一个抗碰撞的哈希函数，我们看如何简单地构建一个MAC
particular, let's see how we can trivially
build a MAC given a collision resistant
假设我们对短信息有一个MAC
hash function. So, suppose we have a MAC
for short messages. So you should be
大家应该想到了类似于AES的算法，AES可以计算16字节信息的MAC
thinking something like AES, which can MAC
sixteen byte messages. And then, suppose
假设我们有一个哈希函数，是抗碰撞的，它从一个很大的信息空间里取值
we have a hash function, a collision
resistant hash function from a large message
将几个G的信息映射到小的信息空间里
space, that contains gigabyte messages
into our small message space. Say, into
映射到16字节输出。然后我们定义一个新MAC
sixteen byte outputs. Then, basically, we
can define a new MAC, let's call it Ibig,
为长信息的MAC。我们用哈希函数输出值的MAC
which happens to be MAC-ing large
messages. And we'll define it simply by
来定义它。那如何验证MAC呢？
applying the small MAC to the output of
the hash function. And how do we verify a
给定一个标签，我们通过重新计算给定信息的哈希值
MAC? Well, basically, given a tag we
verify it by rehashing the given message
来验证，检查小MAC值是否能验证给定的标签
and then checking that small MAC actually
verifies under the given tag. Okay, so
这是一个非常简单的方法，来为大家证明，抗碰撞可以取一个原型
this is a very simple way to show you how
collision resistance can take a primitive
这个原型设置为短输入，把这个原型扩大成一个可以输入非常多位的原型
that's built for small inputs and expand it
into a primitive that's built for very
事实上，我们将看到的并不是MAC所特有的，
large inputs. And in fact we're going to
see this not just for MAC-s. Later on when
一会我们会讨论数字签名时，我们将做同样的证明
we talk about digital signatures, we're
going to do the same thing. We're going to
我们将建立一个短输入的数字签名机制
build a digital signature scheme for small
inputs and then we're going to use
然后我们将用抗碰撞来扩大输入空间，并把它扩大成我们想要的大小
collision resistance to expand the input
space and make it as large as we want. So
所以这个安全性定理的证明并不繁琐
the security theorem basically isn't
something that's trivial here. Basically
这个定理说明了如果在底层MAC之下是安全的，并且H就是抗碰撞的
it says if the underlying MAC is secure
and H is collision resistant, then the
那么这个组合可以计算长信息的MAC，并且MAC是安全的
combination which can actually MAC large
messages, is also a secure MAC. And as
举个简单的例子，我们把这个应用到AES，用一个我们之前说到过的关于SHA-256的例子
a quick example, let's apply this to AES.
So let's use the one example that we
在AES-256中，输出256比特，也就是32字节
mentioned, SHA-256. So in this
case SHA-256 outputs 256 bit outputs,
所以我们需要建立一个可以处理32字节的MAC
which is 32 bytes. So we have to build a
MAC that can MAC 32 byte messages. And the
我们可以应用16字节的AES
way we could do that is basically by
applying the sixteen byte AES, plugging it
把它带入到一个两个分组的CBC，两个分组的CBC可以把16字节的PRF扩展成32字节的
into a two block CBC. A two block CBC
would expand AES from a PRF on sixteen
然后取SHA-256的输出，并带入到
bytes to a PRF on 32 bytes. And then take
the output of SHA-256 and plug it into
基于AES的这两个分组，然后我们得到一个非常简单的MAC
this two block CBC based on AES. And then
we get a very, very simple, MAC which is
当AES是个PRF并且SHA-256是抗碰撞的
secure assuming AES is a PRF and SHA-256
is collision resistant. So one thing I
我想说明的是抗碰撞是这个机制正常工作的必要条件
wanted to point out is that in fact
collision resistance is necessary for this
事实上，抗碰撞比不只是一个人造术语
construction to work. So in fact,
collision resistance is not just a made-up
抗碰撞是这个组合MAC是安全的本质
term. Collision resistance really is kind
of the essence of why this combined MAC is
让我们暂时假设我们正使用的哈希函数H
secure. And so let's just assume for a
minute that the function H, the hash
H不是一个抗碰撞的，换句话说
function we're using, is not collision
resistant. In other words, there is an
存在一个算法，可以找到两个不同的信息可以有相同的输出
algorithm that can find two distinct
messages that happen to map to the same
在这种情况下，组合MAC是不安全的
output. In this case, the combined MAC. Is
not going to be secure because what the
因为攻击者简单的使用一个人选择信息攻击来获得m0的标签
adversary can do is simply use a chosen
message attack to get a tag for m0. And
然后输出m1它的标签是伪造的，确实，T是m1的一个有效MAC
then output m1 comma that tag as a forgery
and indeed T is a valid MAC for m1 because
因为H（m1）=H（m0），只需要选择一个信息攻击，
H(m1) happens to be equal to H(m0). And
so in doing so just with a one chosen
攻击则就可以简单的破解组合MAC
message attack the attacker was able to
break this combined MAC simply because the
因为哈希函数是非抗碰撞的 。我想强调一下
hash function was not collision resistant.
So it should be, again I want to emphasize
如果有人宣布哪怕只有一个SHA-256的碰撞
that if someone advertised even one
collision for SHA-256, you know two
只要有两个信息，只要有一对信息在SHA-256有相同的输出
messages, just one pair of messages that
happen to have the same output under
就会使这个机制不安全
SHA-256 that would already make this
construction insecure cause an attacker
因为攻击者可以访问一个信息的标签，同时他也将获得另一个信息的标签
could then ask for the tag on one message
and in doing so he would obtain the tag on
这将会形成一个存在性伪证
the other message as well, and that would
count as an existential forgery. Okay, so
我们已经知道抗碰撞是一个非常有用的原型
already, we see the collision resistance
is a very useful primitive, in that it
它使我们可以扩展密码学原型的输入空间
lets us expand the input space of
cryptographic primitives. I wanna show you
我要向你们再展示一个应用，在这个应用中抗碰撞被直接的应用于信息的完整性
one more application where a collision
resistance is directly used for message
想象一下，我们有要保护的文件
integrity. Imagine again, we have files that we
wanna protect. Let's imagine these files
假设这些文件是软件包，我们想把它们安装在系统里
are actually software packages that, we
wanna install on our system. So here are
这里有三个不同的软件包。一个也许是GCC，一个是Emacs
three different software packages. You
know, maybe one is GCC, on is Emacs, and
还有一个，我不确定。现在用户想下载软件包
another one is, I don't know, VI. Now the
user wants to download the software
他想要确保他下载的软件包的版本
package and he wants to make sure that he
really did get a version of the package
不是被攻击者篡改过内容的版本
that he downloaded and it's not some
version that the attacker tampered with
那么用户可以参考一个比较小的只读公共空间
and modified its contents. So what he
could do is basically refer to a read-only
这个公共空间只需要保存这些软件包的哈希值
public space that's relatively small. All
it has to do is hold small hashes of these
不需要很多这样的空间，唯一的要求就是这个空间是只读的
software packages. So there isn't a lot of
space needed here. The only requirement is
换句话说，攻击者不能篡改在这个空间里的哈希函数值
that this space is read-only. In other
words, the attacker cannot modify the
然后一旦用户参考了公共空间，
hashes stored in this space. And then,
once he consults this public space, he can
他就可以非常容易的计算出他下载的包的哈希值，将这个值与公共空间的值相比较
very easily compute the hash of a package
that he downloaded. Compare it to the
如果这两者相等，则他下载包的版本是正确的
value in the public space. And if the two
match. Then he knows that the version of
为什么?
the package he downloaded is, in fact, a
correct one. Why is that true? Well,
因为函数H是抗碰撞的，攻击者找不到F1的路径
because the function H is collision
resistant. The attacker cannot find an F1
可以让它拥有和F1相同的哈希函数
path, they would have the same hash as F1.
And as a result, the attacker cannot
因为攻击者无法在不被监测出来的情况下篡改F1的值
modify F1 without being detected because
there's no way that the hash of his F1
因为没有办法使F1映射成存储在公共空间里的值
[inaudible] would map to the value that's
stored in the public space. So, the reason
我将这个例子的原因是，我想把它和MAC的例子作比较
I brought up this example is, I wanted to
contrast this with the MAC example. We
我们看一个MAC的类似情况，在这个MAC的例子里
kinda saw a similar situation with MAC-s.
In the MAC example, we needed a secret key
我们需要你个密钥来验证单个文件的标签，但我们不需要一个只读的公共空间资源
to verify the individual file tags. But we
didn't need a resource that was a read
利用抗碰撞的函数
only public space. With
collision-resistant hashes, we kind of get
我们就可以不用一个密钥来验证。任何人都可以验证
the exact compliment where in fact we
don't need a key to verify. Anyone can
你不需要你一个密码要验证，但是，我们突然需要这个额外的资源
verify. You don't need a secret key for
it. However, now all of a sudden we need
这个资源是攻击者无法篡改的空间
this extra resource which is some space
that the attacker cannot modify. And, in
事实上，我们稍后将看到数字签名
fact, later on, we're gonna see that with
digital signatures, we can kind get to the
我们可以在完整性和资源两方面达到最优，并且不需要只读空间
best of both worlds, where we have both
public verifiability, and we don't need a
但是，只有MAC或者抗碰撞，我们只能达成单方面的要求
read only space. But so far, with either
MAC-s or collision resistance, we can have
我将告诉大家的是，事实上，这种机制很流行
one, but not the other. So, I'll tell you
that, in fact, this kind of scheme is very
实际上，Linux发行版通常使用公共空间
popular. In fact, Linux distributions
often use public space where they
来发布软件包的哈希值
advertise hashes of their software
packages. And anyone can make sure that
在装入电脑之前，任何人可以确保他们下载的软件包的值是正确的
they downloaded the right software package
before installing it on their computer. So
这是在现实中广泛应用的
this is, in fact, something that's used
quite extensively in the real world. Okay,
下一节我们将讨论对抗碰撞的通用攻击
so in the next segment we'll talk about
generic attack on collision resistance and
我们还会继续构建抗碰撞哈希函数
then we'll go ahead and build collision
resistant hash functions.